I think we can all agree that this game is missing something quite crucial, something fundamental and
absolutely necessary to all games.
And that is score.
Because how are you going to flex to your friends when you can't even show them a high score?
In putting in a scoring feature, you will be learning one of the most fundamental programming concepts
and you'll be using a code block we have not touched yet, and that is variables.
So are you ready to continue with your learning adventure?
Looking at our game, what we want is a little score at the top that indicates how many times we have
headed the ball, and we want the score to reset if we miss.
So moving over to the variables code group, you can see that there are actually not that many code
blocks here.
And for code blocks that are considered so important, you might be thinking this area should be stacked.
Well, unlike all the other code block groups that we've looked at with variables, you can actually
make more code blocks by clicking on this button here, which we will look at in a minute.
But before we do this, I just want you to understand what variables are.
Now, in programming, we often need to store information so that we can use it later on.
And we also need a way to get this information easily.
This is where variables come in.
Variables are like containers that hold information and that's why they called variables.
It basically means the container can hold various types of information.
We can give variables names so that we can easily access them and put information into them, and use
the information wherever we need it.
Think of variables like boxes that we can store things in, just like you might have a box to store
your games, a box to store your books, a box to store your old socks, or whatever.
Variables are pretty much the same, but instead of storing physical objects like books and games and
stinky old socks, variables store data like numbers and text.
So picture it like this.
We have a variable called score, and inside this variable we are storing the value zero.
But when I play gets a header, we go back, look inside our variable box scored score to discover what
value is currently inside the variable.
And so in this case when we look inside it, it's zero.
Now that we've looked inside the box and discovered it's zero, we can simply add one which gives us
one and store that back into the box.
Then we can display our variable and the score of one is displayed on the screen.
When we get another header, what does the program do?
It'll go back, look inside the score box.
And this time it'll see that it has number one stored in there.
We can simply add one to this which now gives us two.
Store that back inside our variable and display that on the screen.
And obviously it goes on and on.
But basically I want you to understand how variables are just digital storage boxes with names.
And these named variables can store any number of text and numbers etc...
And we can easily check what values our variables have.
And we can use our variables in a number of ways, such as keeping our score for our game or even in
invisible behind the scenes way, like increasing the difficulty of the game as we all look at later
on.
So now that you understand the basic idea of variables, let's take a look at these blocks and see how
they relate to what we said.
Firstly, remember how I said the variables group lets you create new blocks?
Well, to do that we just need to click on this button and this makes a new variable.
So basically a new box to store our digital information.
And as you can see it asks what we want to call the variable.
Because this is going to hold our score information.
We will call it score.
Then just below this.
See how it gives us a decision?
Is this variable for all sprites or is it for this sprite only?
Now basically what this means is can all the other sprites see and modify our score variable, or can
only this sprite access it?
So in programming this is what we call scope.
And that's just like a fancy word for what part of the code can see or modify variables.
If all sprites can see and modify the variable, that is called a global scope, while this sprite only
can see and modify it, that is a local scope variable.
We will choose the sprite only as our other sprite.
Don't need to have access to our score variable and all the modifications can happen inside the sprite.
And clicking okay.
Here you can see our brand new score variable appearing here.
And look how you can even see it on the screen, which in this case works perfectly for us.
So now that we have our variable, I'm going to drag each of these blocks out so you can see what they
do.
So firstly we have set the variable to a number.
And if you change this number and click it, well nothing happens.
And that's just because we haven't selected our score variable.
Doing so you will now see our score is set to three as reflected on the screen.
So this block over here doesn't care what our variable was, it just sets it to whatever value we want.
And this could even be a word like hi.
But we want to keep it as a number.
So let's set it back to zero.
Moving down to our next variable.
This one is to change the value.
So if we were to put one here and then click see our score increases by one.
And basically what this block is doing is what I explained earlier.
When I click it it looks at what value is stored in our score variable, which in this case is two.
And then it looks at what value it needs to be changed by which is one.
So it takes two, adds one.
And you've done the math in your head.
Very good.
And we get a score of three.
And finally looking down, we have these two blocks which are quite simple.
We can show a variable on our stage or we can hide it well.
That's all there is to it.
And with that, you now understand the fundamentals of variables and programming, which is a super,
super important concept.
And I want you to try now and see if you can implement the score variable into your code.
And in the next lesson I will show you how we did it.